Chapter 1: I feel a need for books

The restricted section of the Hogwarts library was, unsurprisingly, off limits to students. From under his cloak of invisibility Harry observed the fearsome barrier. A couple of poles and some half inch diameter rope suspended waist high.

It was fearsome, of course, by convention. Because it was prohibited. Because Madam Pince, the librarian, may notice if you stepped over the rope there without having provided a note signed by a professor. Because you might get a severe talking to.

Harry was an expert at being reprimanded. He would prefer to avoid it, all other things being equal, but at least he was sure that even in the madness that was Hogwarts, there would be no mortal danger from some tripwire. There was, of course, mortal danger in the books, but that was different. Books were Harry's friends.

The big question was whether there was more serious security than a rope and wandering librarian. In the muggle world, blueprints of nuclear bombs had more protection than a piece of rope in a school library. And there were potentially magics described over there far more destructive than a critical mass of uranium.

But then, security at Hogwarts was a joke. And the true cloak of invisibility would bypass most detection charms – at least those aimed at detecting people, rather than the movement of books. More prosaic detection systems wouldn't be fooled by the cloak. Harry had weighed himself while wearing the cloak. Gravity was not fooled - the scales showed the same result regardless of whether the cloak was hiding him.

To make a secure system, there are two approaches. For the correct approach, you need to clearly think about what you are trying to secure, and all possible attacks. The alternative, more popular approach, is to think of one possible attack, and defend carefully against that. That is a much simpler, more intuitive algorithm, and it leads to multiple strong locks on a door with hinges on the outside, or steel reinforced doors adjacent to thin glass windows. It leads to keeping Hermione at Hogwarts, for safety.

Harry noticed that his fists were clenched painfully. He consciously released them. Think clearly, Harry. You are going to do this. Nothing is going to stop you. Not Dumbledore, not whoever had killed Hermione, not even death itself. Nothing. Death was the enemy, and Harry refused to lose. Relax and think carefully.

Evidence: Dumbledore's previous behaviour. Conclusion: Dumbledore would have taken the popular approach. Therefore there was almost certainly a way to bypass whatever security the headmaster had set up for the restricted section, assuming he could work out what it was he had to bypass. But Harry didn't know enough magic to detect what charms Dumbledore had used. He would have to guess.

Hypothesis: The security is aimed at people rather than books. How could he test this, while maintaining plausible deniability? He could use minions, but that seemed unfair on them. Madam Pince was nowhere near. Harry took off his cloak of invisibility. Sure, he wore it routinely as a general security measure, but the use of it did unfairly prejudice observers if he had to protest his innocence. He waited until Madam Pince walked past, carrying a couple of books to reshelve. He waved his wand at a book he didn't recognise about two metres away in the unrestricted section of the library. Accio Book, he cast as quietly, as if avoiding disturbing other library patrons. Not that there were any at this hour. The book wafted gently over to him. Harry caught it – 99 popular uses of herbs - in his hands, and pretended to read it until Madam Pince was out of sight. Then he turned towards the restricted section, chose a book in his mind, and cast Accio Book again, bracing for an alarm.

The alarm did not come. Neither did the book. Harry sighed, and replaced 99 popular uses of herbs in its proper spot, and put his invisibility cloak back on. That was his least desired outcome. If the book had come to him, with no alarms, he would have succeeded. If the book had come to him with alarms, then he could claim he had just mis-targeted his charm, and he would know more about the security system. But now all he knew was that at least one charm was blocked somehow.

There weren't many other options for him now. He could ask Professor Quirrell for a blanket permission slip. But even if the defence professor cooperated, it was not clear that this would be a long term solution. The restricted section was big. It would take him a long time to read enough of them. There would be plenty of time for Professor McGonagall or Dumbledore to notice and ask questions, and put a stop to it. He could ask Professor Quirrell for specific books – or books on certain subjects. That request would probably be successful – the defence professor had promised to help, after all. But the help may be censored, and Harry would have no way of telling.

None of the books would have a resurrection spell in them. Harry was pretty sure about that. Such a spell would hardly be obscure, even if it was impractical for most situations. Actually, it was surprising that there weren't even any rumours of resurrection spells, even if they were no more credible than the philosopher's stone ought to be.

Harry had identified four approaches to resurrecting Hermione.

Make up a resurrection spell.

Make up a "become god" spell, then use godlike power to make up a resurrection spell.

Find the Philosopher's stone, should it actually exist, and work out how to use it.

Other.

All four required more information, which probably wasn't even in the restricted stacks, but trying them couldn't hurt. Well, that was not exactly true. Sometimes a fresh way of looking at things was helpful, whereas reading what other people did would just give him a cognitive bias towards the unsuccessful class of approaches described in them. Harry's mouth twitched upwards at one side. Not looking at things the same way everyone else does was one of his core competencies.

Time was passing, Hermione's brain would be very slowly losing coherence, and someone was targeting his friends. It was time to try a riskier approach. Harry picked five particularly boring books from the unrestricted section, and then checked that the cloak was covering him. It was. He poked a foot under the rope barrier. "I was just sitting down here to read this book, and moved to be comfortable and accidentally stuck my leg under the rope" was somewhat plausible, if not convincing.

No alarm seemed to be going off. Harry waited there carefully for five minutes. Madam Pince did not come around.

Harry put the cloak back on, rolled his whole body through, and padded over to the bookcases. He skimmed over the titles – too many, too many – and chose five that may conceivably have something to do with spell creation. He replaced them with books of roughly the same size from the collection he had brought over from the unrestricted section. Lastly he padded back to the rope, under it, and back to the unrestricted side.

The piercing sound of alarms did not fill the library. That was worryingly easy.

Harry sat down to browse the first of his liberated books, "Magical Catastrophes"

Several minutes later, Harry had started on the fourth book, "Dark rituals for fun and profit". All three previous ones had passed the "worth studying in detail" test, although it was hard to tell for sure.

He jumped when he heard Professor McGonagall's voice a couple of metres behind him. "Mr. Potter. Please show me what you are reading. Now."

Still under the cloak, Harry quickly stuffed "Dark rituals for fun and profit" back into his pouch with the others, and pulled out "Magical Catastrophes". That would be easier to explain. Then he took off his cloak and turned around towards her. He held out the forbidden book. She glanced at the title, and coldly said "Please come back with me to my office."

They walked in uncomfortable silence, Professor McGonagall holding the book. When they eventually arrived in her office, she indicated at the guest chair with her wand, and sat in her own. She fixed him with a sad stare that hurt Harry more than any reprimand could.

"The centaurs believe that I am going to unintentionally cause a catastrophe," he said before she could start the conversation elsewhere.

"And you decided to do it intentionally instead? Or were you just curious about how you would do it?"

"No!" Harry paused "Well, yes, of course I was curious, but that is entirely incidental. I want to know how not to cause a catastrophe. For that I need to know what not to do."

"Most people manage to get through their whole lives without causing a catastrophe. Most of them would even say that 'don't do things that are forbidden as they are dangerous' is a good first step to not causing a catastrophe."

"But most people do not already have the centaurs prophesising that they will cause a catastrophe. Professor Quirrell is independently worried. For me to avoid disaster, I need to actively do something different."

"Don't you think that obeying the carefully considered rules would count as different for you?"

"That's… not a bad point." Harry shrunk back into his seat. They may be carefully considered, but that doesn't mean they are sensible. But it also doesn't mean they are not. Why do I never think of the obvious, non-Harry-plan-centric view? Then he realised, and sat back up. "Sorry, forget that. It is a bad point. That is the sort of thinking that got Hermione killed." Professor McGonagall flinched. "I need to be able to defend my friends."

"More than you need to prevent a catastrophe?"

"Yes, I know the road to hell is paved in good intentions, but… "

"But you are different?"

"No! Yes! I am a scientist. I am rational. I understand that a small chance of disaster is not negligible."

"You don't make mistakes?"

This time it was Harry who flinched. "The more information I have, the better decisions I can make."

"I don't think that is true, Harry. If you don't know how to destroy the world, then you generally can't effectually decide to do so. If you have the information on how to destroy the world, then you can make a really bad decision."

"But I already know how to destroy the world! That's easy!" Harry realized how bad that sounded. "I mean, not as such, but I am sure I could come up with a couple of avenues for exploration given some thought. Destruction is easy. I could create a paradox with my time turner somehow, for instance." Harry kicked himself when he saw Professor McGonagall staring pensively at his chest where his time turner lay. "Not that I would, of course. Remember how terrified I was of it when you first gave it to me. There are lots of other ways. I could transfigure a huge pile of nuclear weapons. Or antimatter. Destruction is easy."

"You are not reassuring me."

"But I would have to be insane to do any of those things!"

"How many people in this school believe you to be sane, Harry?"

"But they are all wrong. Sure, many people think that I am mad because I behave rationally rather than following a script, but that is actually evidence of sanity. The people who really know me know that."

"The people who really know you are concerned about how Hermione's death has affected you."

"Oh." Harry deflated. In his heart he knew that the hypothesis Harry has gone insane was not one he could categorically rule out.

"And if you knew some powerful, dangerous magic, can you say with absolute certainty that you would not have used it in the battle against the troll, under time pressure, with your best friend bleeding to death in front of you?"

Harry didn't answer.

"Harry, we give transfiguration texts to first year students. The restricted books are really dangerous."

Silence stretched on for a while. "Thank you," said Harry at last. "Thank you for not just telling me off for being a naughty boy. Thank you for going off script and trying to give me useful advice and reasonable arguments. Thank you for treating me as an adult. That means so much to me."

"Does that mean I have convinced you?"

"No," said Harry slowly. "No, I cannot say that I am convinced. But neither am I convinced of my own position any more. I need to think about this for a while. Ummm. I have something to ask your opinion on. About my sanity. I want to see if you agree with Professor Quirrell."

"Go on."

"I want to resurrect Hermione."

"Impossible."

"Sorry, I phrased that incorrectly. I intend to resurrect Hermione."

"Intention doesn't make it possible."

"Sorry, I phrased that incorrectly. I will resurrect Hermione."

"Harry – I understand what it is like to lose a friend. But many, many wise and powerful magi have tried and failed. It is not possible. Believing it is possible is not sanity. Has Professor Quirrell been encouraging you?" Her voice was much sharper for the last question.

"No. He has been working hard to discourage me. He agrees with you that it is impossible, and I am mad to try. Actually, he thinks I am mad to want to do so, but that's just his issues showing. But not trying just because something is said to be impossible is wrong. Remember the partial transfiguration?"

"I do. Whenever I feel insufficiently terrified, I solve that problem by thinking of it."

"I've got so many things I need to do," said Harry in a steadily rising voice. I need to defend my friends against whoever is targeting them. I need to defeat you-know-who, should he still actually be alive. To do that I probably need to find out what power I have that the dark lord knows not. I need to destroy the blight that is Azkhaban. And I desperately need to not cause a catastrophe in the process. I need to save the world from lots of problems it generally is unaware it has. I need to not die before doing all these things. I need to not make any mistakes." His voice suddenly became quiet. "But there is just one thing that I want. I want to resurrect Hermione. Oh, and the defence professor too. Not that he is dead yet, but that should make fixing him easier."

Minerva looked at the first year with tenderness. So much we demand of him. So little we can offer him.

"You know if there is anything I could do to help, I would. But there isn't."

"But there is. I am going to get the power that the dark lord knows not. I am going to learn how to do the impossible – at least what he thinks is impossible. Everyone says that he is clever, so if he thinks something is inconceivable then probably most others do to. I have the power to conceive the inconceivable – yes, I understand that one could argue that is evidence that I am insane - but I need help. Concrete example: can I run any ideas that I come up with by you, as a sanity check?"

"Of course."

"And will you promise to take them seriously, and acknowledge the necessity of doing something?"

Professor McGonagall paused. It was not that the request was unreasonable, she just wanted to convince herself that she would actually be able to follow through with it. She finally replied, "Yes, as long as you promise to take my warnings seriously."

"Perfectly fair. I so promise. By the way, Professor Quirrell also promised to help me."

"What?"

"After trying hard to dissuade me from my resolve to resurrect Hermione, he offered to help."

"How?"

"By getting me information, among other things."

"So why didn't you get him to get you the restricted books?"

"I don't trust him. I don't trust him not to censor them."

Professor McGonagall paused, and said in a hesitating manner, "You have reason. I don't know if I should be saying this but… ten minutes ago it was he who told me you had gone into the restricted section of the library. He said it would be more effective for me to tell you off than him."

"What! Why is he doing security for the restricted section?"

"He recently added some of his own security. He is afraid of you."

"What? Professor Quirrell is afraid of me? He is absurdly powerful and smart and creative and devious and paranoid. He shouldn't be afraid of anyone."

"Harry, half the people who know you are afraid of you, and the other half are foolish. Or Griffindors." She paused, reflecting. "Foolish Griffindors. You successfully threatened some of the most powerful wizards in Britain at the Wizardgamot… and they had no idea of your true potential. Even dementors are scared of you. You calmly dismiss the threat of you know who. I, the head of Griffindor house, I am afraid of you, and I trust you to be well intentioned towards me."

Harry's face had grown steadily more horrified as she spoke. Minerva started speaking again. "Suppose you decided that you really wanted the defence professor dead. How long would he live?"

Less than a day, Harry thought as he considered the muggle materials he had got the Weasley twins to procure for him. "But I like him. I approve of life. I want to make the world a better place. I only want to destroy evil."

"Even so, would you ever think the ends justify the means?" It was obvious from Harry's expression what the answer was. She didn't wait for him to answer it. "But he is not, I think, worried about you actively going after him. He is worried about the mistakes you might make. Mistakes that humanity would not survive. Tell me Harry. Who scares you the most?"

Harry looked at the floor. He wanted to say the person targeting Hogwarts students. But that was not true. They were a minor threat. Once identified, he was pretty confident he could neutralize them somehow… probably by telling Dumbledore who it was. Or the defence professor if it were Dumbledore. Look at it impartially - what would the sorting hat say. That didn't need much thought. There was only one person he truly feared. "Myself," he said in a small voice.

"In your first few week at school you threatened myself, Professor Snape, and even the headmaster. They you started new research in transfiguration. Now you are searching the restricted section of the library. Am I wrong to be afraid of you?"

Harry suddenly straightened. She could see the self-confidence returning to him. "No, you are perfectly right to be afraid. So is Professor Quirrell. It is just that the idea of him being afraid is like the idea of Snape having a beloved pet bunny rabbit called Flopsy. I was distracted by the absurdity. You are correct to be afraid of me, but you should be even more afraid of a world without me."

"You mean because of you-know-who?"

"No, he is harmless compared to my real enemy. I mean death. It is not me you are scared of directly. It is not even what I might do. It is death you are scared of. Not for yourself, maybe, but for everyone. You are scared that I might cause everyone to die. Similarly, you are not scared of you know who. You are scared of the death and misery to many that he could bring. True?"

"Yes, but I don't think the distinction is anything other than pedantry."

"You fear death. That is the point. Consider that if I don't do something about it, you will die, as will everyone you know and care about. It may be an accident that gets them, or malice, or merely old age. But they will all die."

Harry paused for rhetorical impact, but started again before Minerva could interject. "I do not fear death. I hate death. I consider death to be an enemy to be vanquished. That is why the dementors fear me. I may not succeed, but if I fail others like me – and just as scary as me - will continue the fight. Eventually one of us will win, and humanity will look back on the era of death as a dystopia of fear and misery. You are right to be scared of me, but you should be even more scared of that which I will fight."

Professor McGonagall stared at Harry for almost a minute. Then she smiled. "If Gryffindor himself were here, I believe he would applaud. I am not him." Suddenly fire burned in her eyes. "But I have just decided to do something very Griffindor. I am about to do something ridiculously brave and stupid because my heart says it is the right thing to do. I am going to give you free access to the restricted section of the library, as long as you solemnly promise to run anything you come up with as a result by me. Do you so promise?"

"I do. I swear by my love for humanity to sanity check any ideas I get from the restricted section by you."

They talked for a while longer, about how to bypass Professor Quirrell's alarms. They settled on the obvious solution. Professor McGonagall would just get them for Harry, one bunch at a time. Harry requested ones related to disasters, healing, and the philosopher's stone. Minerva flinched slightly at the mention of the stone, but didn't say anything. Harry decided it was the wrong time to press.

Harry walked back to his dorm somewhat happily. Professor McGonagall was off script. The world was good. As long as he was sane, that is. If not… the world was in trouble.

Chapter 3: My Precious

Before playing with his new toy, Harry wanted to check that is was safe.

He had briefly been concerned merely by the claimed function. This is a device that alters - ostensibly improves - how your brain works. Harry was quite proud of his brain, and was rather attached to it. The potential side effects were terrifying, let alone personality change. But, frankly, that wasn't going to stop him using it. Not if it could help him save Hermione. Besides, he hoped that Rowena Ravenclaw was wise enough on the occupational health and safety front, although the artefact did end up in a tree in Albania, if the defence professor could be trusted.

What he was really concerned about was the possibility of dark magic being overlaid. Well, clearly there was some dark magic already there, possibly a Lord Voldemort Horcrux, but that could be a blind. The defence professor had shown strong evidence of wanting to manipulate Harry down a particular path. He presumably couldn't use direct mind control magic on Harry for the same reason their magic didn't seem to work on each other. If the defence professor were out to control Harry, then a subverted mind controlling artefact that would be irresistible to Harry would be difficult to top as a perfect trap. And that was ignoring the possibility of a genuine Lord Voldemort Horcrux on it.

The feeling of doom that Harry got around the artefact didn't help either. Actually, it did. Suppose that the defence professor was correct about the Horcrux. Suppose further that the feeling of doom was associated with the Horcrux. Suppose that the reason the feelings of doom were similar was because the defence professor also had – or was – a Lord Voldemort Horcrux. Possibly Quirinus Quirrell had triggered a Horcrux, and been possessed by Lord Voldemort, or at least partly so. That was a lot of suppositions – a stiff complexity penalty should be applied.

What would the mixture of a maybe decent person and Lord Voldemort be? If the defence professor was correct about himself being part possessed by Lord Voldemort, then Harry was an example of the species. There were a lot of ways that could go. It certainly was not inconsistent with the defence professor's power, personality, and mysterious past.

Harry shook himself. Such speculation was important, but he had a shiny toy to play with. For all his misgivings, it took immense self control to not put it on right now.

Dumbledore would be the obvious person to ask about it, but Harry was somewhat leery of trusting him. Furthermore, Professor McGonagall deserved trust, and positive reinforcement. It was to her offices that he ran. After thirty seconds, he jumped on his broomstick. The less time he took to get to her office, the less time he had to resist putting it on.

Fortunately she was in his office, and called him in when he knocked.

"Harry! Don't tell me you have finished that set already?"

"No, sorry. I can't read that fast. Let along absorb and think about it. No, the defence professor just gave me the most powerful magical artefact I have ever heard of... and I want you to check it for booby traps."

She looked up in shock. "He gave you the elder wand? Not the Philospher's Stone?"

"No, no, way beyond them." He brought out the diadem. "Rowena's artefact. Mind magic has the greatest potential for ... umm... greatness." Harry couldn't understand why everyone else didn't see this.

Professor McGonagall accepted the proffered piece of jewellery. It did indeed look like the pictures, and a cursory scan indicated that it was indeed endowed with significant magic. "This will take some time. It would probably be better to take to the headmaster, you know. He could do a better job than me."

"I trust him 95%. I trust you 100%. Please go ahead, I'll wait."

Minerva was shocked at the effect of his offhand declaration of trust towards her. She had lost much of her never particularly high trust in herself over Hermione's death. She had come to trust many of Harry's judgements - at least the ones that were not self-centred - and it appeared that he trusted her. Unlike Dumbledore, Harry wouldn't say it just to make her feel better. For the first time in her life, she thought that she might actually make a decent headmistress when and if her time came. She snorted to herself. It was pretty pathetic that such validation should come from a first year student.

She focussed on her work. First task was to determine if it were genuine. That was relatively easy. After only a minute and a half she looked up and informed him that she was quite sure it was the true diadem.

Searching for booby traps was more difficult. First a simple search for dark magic. Oh. "I have some bad news. There is some very powerful dark charm on the diadem. It is not part of the original enchantment. I will attempt to determine what it is." She spent another ten minutes, trying test after test. "The bad news is that I can't identify it for sure. It doesn't seem to do anything. I suspect that it may be a Horcrux. We should really take this to the headmaster. He has more knowledge of Horcruxes than me."

"I thought you might say that. The defence professor warned me that he thought it had a you-know-who Horcrux on it. He claimed that it was unlikely to ensnare me. I didn't want to prejudice your examination by telling you in advance. Although if it looked as if you were about to put it on, I would have stopped you, of course."

"Despite this, you are still considering it? Can you imagine how terrible it would be if you were to become his host? Possibly that is what the prophecy meant by 'EITHER MUST DESTROY ALL BUT A REMNANT OF THE OTHER.' Could its power possibly be worth the risk?"

"I don't know. That is why I am asking you about it. It depends how big the risk it, versus the potential gain of giving me a significant advantage in a later confrontation with you-know-who."

Minerva considered it carefully. "This is beyond my area of expertise. I strongly recommend that we go to see the headmaster."

"I am happy to go to Professor Dumbledore then. Thank you."

"I haven't finished yet. I've checked for dark magic, but not for superficially harmless charms that could have less innocent uses. Give me a few more minutes." Before returning to the task she asked a witch in a painting behind her to see if the headmaster was in and free. She continued experimenting. By the time the witch had returned to her painting she had finished. There were no other charms.

The headmaster was indeed available, so they proceeded directly to his office. The door to the spiral staircase opened as they approached, the stairs twisting upwards.

Dumbledore sighed when he saw the two of them. "It is a bad sign when the two of you show up in my office," he greeted them. "Historically, at least. What has happened this time?"

Professor McGonagall replied, "Actually, it is quite good news." One of Dumbledore's eyebrows rose. "Harry was given Rowena's diadem by the defence professor. He asked me to check it for traps. I am convinced that it is genuine, but it has a strong black charm on it. I have suspicions as to its nature, but I would like your opinion too."

"May I see?"

Minerva handed the diadem to the headmaster. She watched him study it, noting many of the same spells she had used.

"It is a Horcrux. Almost certainly Voldemort's," he finally concluded. "This is excellent news. We can destroy it, and that will be one step closer to his end."

"No," interjected Harry in alarm. "At least not until we have considered the alternatives. Unless - are you talking about just destroying the Horcrux, or the whole artefact?"

"The whole artefact, I am afraid, Harry. A Horcrux is too powerful to do otherwise."

"But Ravenclaw's diadem is the most useful item known to humanity!"

"Disposing of one of Voldemort's Horcruxes is of immense use to humanity."

"Could we hold off for a little, please? Does the Horcrux pose a direct threat to the wearer?"

"I do not believe it does. But Voldemort only has a small number of Horcruxes. The destruction of a single one would be valuable. Voldemort will only be genuinely dead when all are destroyed."

"It doesn't make sense," interjected Harry suddenly. "The diadem is a dumb place for a Horcrux."

"Why so?"

"Well, it is easy to notice and destroy, and hard to safeguard. More importantly, it is such a useful artefact that the possessor would want to wear it. A Horcrux, on the other hand, should be stored far away from its creator for redundancy purposes. It just doesn't make sense."

"On the contrary, it makes perfect sense," said the headmaster. "A Horcrux can be a trap. An unwary person might find a diadem, and put it on. This could trigger the Horcrux to take over their mind. So it makes sense to put it on a powerful artefact as it is a greater temptation to put it on."

Harry looked at his precious with some trepidation. "Is that an automatic property of a Horcrux, or does it need some other trigger?"

"It needs some other trigger. I couldn't find any traces of such a trigger."

"So it is a stupid place," said Harry.

"Maybe," suggested Minerva, "Maybe the other ones are in sensible places, and this one is in a stupid place to confuse us? Or maybe there was such a trigger, but the defence professor removed it."

Harry and Albus nodded weakly, acknowledging plausibility without being totally convinced.

Harry was meanwhile thinking about the Voyager spacecraft, and what an ideal Horcrux it would make, assuming some alien could trigger it. And Professor Quirrell had almost owned up to doing so, assuming of course that he was also a Voldemort mixture. "So there is little point destroying this one until we have found the others?"

"Destroying this one now would prevent us ever losing it," said Minerva pensively. "But there are alternatives. Albus, could you put a charm on it that would enable us to find it later if it were stolen?"

"Probably," allowed the headmaster dubiously.

"Headmaster, is your magic powerful enough to reach the planet Mars," asked Harry suddenly.

"No," said Albus, looking strangely at Harry. "Not even the moon."

"Do you think any other wizard has magic that could reach that far?"

"I would be exceedingly surprised."

"You know the muggles have had several spacecraft fly far beyond Mars. Ones that are never coming back. Ones that are unlikely to encounter anything as big as a speck of dust for the next billion years."

The headmaster and deputy stared at Harry in horror.

"I am sorry, Harry," said the headmaster finally. "If Voldemort is unkillable, and the prophecy says one of you and he are doomed to die, and the signs are showing that the battle is imminent..."

"Don't be defeatist," said Professor McGonagall briskly. "Firstly, if all of you know who is destroyed other than one Horcrux in deep space, then maybe that counts as `all but a remnant of'. In fact, that may fit the prophecy more than anything likely to happen to Harry. Furthermore, even if he keeps living, if his presence is with the spacecraft, it will be a long way away from anywhere he could do harm."

Harry didn't like that idea. It was an argument for the destruction of the diadem. "There are other interpretations. I could be left in a coma, in a vegetable state. That could be construed as `all but a remnant of.' Furthermore, I could always go and bring the spacecraft back."

The other two looked at him in astonishment. "How would you propose to do that," asked the headmaster.

"I don't know. But it is physically possible. I can't think of any particularly moral ways of doing it off hand - I could always imperious the muggle leaders of various countries and get them to mount a retrieval operation. But the cost would be stupendous. Even ignoring the unforgivable nature of the imperious charm, it would cost trillions of pounds - much more than the entire wealth of magical Britain. That money, spent on hospitals, would save the life of hundreds of thousands of people. That is not an acceptable solution. But maybe given time," and the diadem, "I can come up with a better solution. I'm just saying it is hard but not impossible. In the mean time, we should use whatever weapons we have, and my best weapon is my mind." He nodded towards the diadem. And there is my precious. I haven't even put it on, and still the power it may give me is irresistible, despite the clear danger.

The headmaster stared at him intently for several seconds. "Harry, can you imagine any reason why you would want to tear apart the very stars in heaven?"

"For energy," said Harry promptly. "Possibly for building materials. Most of the universe's accessible mass is probably in stars. Eventually humanity will want to use that mass more productively than just fusing it and radiating it indiscriminately. But that would be spread over billions of years at the earliest."

"How about ending the world?"

"That's a little harder. We could want to use the mass to build a Dyson sphere. That is, a huge sphere surrounding the sun with radius similar to the earth's orbit. It would have a surface area absurdly larger than the earth - lots of room for vast numbers of humans. It would make all the sun's output accessible. We will need that room and energy for the population explosion after I conquer death." He paused, and frowned. "But we would not have to make it exactly in earth's orbit, probably. A little outside, and we could adjust albedos so that the temperature was fine. Then we could use other planets, and keep the earth as a place to live on while we are making it. I would quite like to keep the earth afterwards anyway, as a souvenir of our ancestry. Maybe we would have to dismantle it to make the system stable. I don't know the maths of that offhand. Whatever, it is probably negligible compared to other structural problems involved in cosmic engineering, and vastly simpler than tearing the stars apart." Even the Pak only built a ringworld.

Minerva stared at him. It was the matter of fact way he said it that unnerved her, as if he were describing a change of room for some class. Albus was still watching him dubiously. What made him ask, she wondered.

"I think that Harry should be able to make the most use of his weapon," she said. "In fact, I think it appropriate than he should put the diadem on now, while we are here watching and capable of responding appropriately."

Harry needed no more urging. He held out his hand, the headmaster handed it to him somewhat reluctantly, he closed his eyes and put it on his head.

Nothing much seemed to happen. But Harry was short of input at the moment. He opened his eyes. At first everything seemed normal. He turned around and then he realised that he now remembered perfectly everything he had seen since putting the diadem on. Furthermore, as he gazed at the weird and wonderful contraptions around the headmaster's office, he guessed the functionality of two that had stumped him on prior visits.

"It works," said Harry, with a grin. The headmaster cast a few more charms on Harry - they seemed to be for sensing, and Harry could now remember in enough detail that he could probably reproduce them, although he had no idea how to interpret the results. Presumably the headmaster was checking that the dark charm had not activated.

"The dark charm seems quiet," said the headmaster. "You may not be able to see, but the diadem gave off a faint reddish glow when you put it on. I expect that is a result of its ordinary operation. Apparently when Rowena was wearing it there was a bright blue glow."

So it did not work quite as well for him as it did for the person whom it was designed for. Maybe it would improve with practice. Regardless, anything that improved his ability to think was priceless.

There was an obvious experiment to do. Harry took off the diadem. His flawless memory vanished as he did so. He still had some sense of what had passed while he was wearing the diadem, in fact it seemed a little better than he would normally remember. Harry smiled. "It is a wonderful device. Could you please add the locating charm, headmaster?"

He handed the diadem back to the headmaster, who waved his wand over it, then over a gem taken out of a drawer on the side of his desk. "I have made a bond to this gem. While I have the gem, I will be able to track the diadem. But please try not to lose it, Harry. We will have to destroy it at some point." He handed the diadem back to Harry, who instantly put it on his head.

"Now," said Harry, "I need to think for a while."

Chapter 6: Lack of experience

Elsewhen

Tom mastered his instinctive nausea as Myrtle fell down, slain by the Basilisk. Slain by the will, if not the hand of Tom Riddle, precocious and very ambitious student. He hadn't planned this sufficiently in advance. He could think of two rituals to power with her death. Creating a Horcrux, say into his diary was the obvious choice – first get immortality, then he will have time for everything else. But. But it was important to get the Horcruxes perfect, and he wasn't absolutely sure about it. He needed more knowledge, more intelligence first.

So it would have to be the other way round. Knowledge and intelligence first. He used her death to summon the largest nearby intelligence of the dead.

It came from somewhere unrecognisable.

It was strong.

Present

The defence professor felt the power flowing into him. The missing part of Tom Riddle that had been lodged in Harry bifurcated. The smaller part went back in time; the larger part flowed directly to the defence professor in the present. He felt strong. The fragment had flourished in Harry's fertile mind and was far greater than the amount lost when his Lord Voldemort puppet burned in the Harry Potter fiasco.

The small amount of decency that the venal Quirinus Quirrell had provided was swamped by the strength of Tom's reascending personality. Even thirty seconds ago, the defence professor had been unsure if he could fully go through with his plan. Those doubts were gone. His fondness for the child at his feet was swamped by the anger at people who had not looked up to David Monroe. People who thought more highly of a baby saved by a time loop than of a grown man actively putting himself in harm's way again and again to protect the ungrateful wretches.

Harry fell forward, unconscious. The professor cast enervate at him. It worked. Harry crawled to his knees. The professor had been fairly sure that the time loop would be fully resolved now, and that the immunity Harry had possessed to his magic would be gone, but it was a relief to have it actually shown correct. He smiled. In minutes he would be in Harry's body - the body of the popular hero that the Monroe puppet never was.

Just in case, Tom, as he now thought of himself, cast a powerful finite incantatem at Harry. There was a tiny chance the boy would retain enough sentience to repeat a previous trick. The gem on Harry's ring rapidly grew into the large rock it was naturally. As he suspected, but had not been sure of, the ring itself turned into Hermione's half eaten corpse.

There was a bang and a flash, and Dumbledore was there, McGonagall by his side. The wards had been triggered. Tom smiled. All part of the plan. There would be a big battle; Dumbledore would kill the new Lord Voldemort and Bellatrix Black, cementing his reputation and power. McGonagall would be witness. Unknown to her, the real Tom Riddle would now be inside Harry Potter. Then Harry and Dumbledore together would rule Britain with strength.

Tom hesitated a fraction of a second. It had taken him a long time to persuade Dumbledore that this was the best possible outcome for the world. Ironically it had been easier to persuade Harry of the necessity for his sacrifice to stabilize the time loop than it was for Dumbledore. Hermione's death had almost put Dumbledore off script too.

It had taken letting Dumbledore freely root through his brain to persuade him that it was all true, and that his intention was to honour the agreement.

But Tom was no longer as conscience bound as the entity Dumbledore had read the brain of. The thing was, Tom didn't absolutely need Dumbledore. And he would be much safer in a Dumbledore free world. While Dumbledore and McGonagall were raising their wands, Tom cast Avada Kedavra at Dumbledore in half the time that Lord Voldemort had ever publically demonstrated.

Harry's hand had reappeared, having presumably been under his invisibility cloak. It was holding an artefact of vast power. The philosopher's stone, it must be. Not a threat. His lips were whispering something. Not important.

McGonagall though had reacted faster than Tom had anticipated. Half a second was all that was needed for the transfiguration expert to convert Tom's wand into a pumpkin. Tom didn't waste time castigating himself. He physically punched her, hard, and she went down, winded. Tom fell with her, pinning her wand arm and preventing a follow through. On the ground near Harry he grabbed the wand, twin to his original, from Harry's unresisting hand. Harry was saying something like "Becomus" Tom turned back to the somewhat stunned Minerva. He needed her to survive, to be a witness to Lord Voldemort losing to Harry Potter again. But he couldn't have her interfering. With Harry's wand he cast a binding spell on her from point blank range.

Tom spun back around to Harry, who had just finished saying something like "Goddus". The philosopher's stone beeped and announced "Insufficient experience points error." Harry screamed "No!" in horror.

The philosopher's stone wasn't totally finished. A beam shone out to each of the people – or bodies – around it. Tom tried to defend, but it went through all his shields. Then he stopped worrying. He felt great! All the accumulated damage from a lifetime of black rituals had vanished.

Study later. Fight now. He cast an absurdly strong Imperius on Harry before further things went wrong, and looked around. Bellatrix was standing tall. He smiled to see it. McGonagall had recovered from her binding spell and had started some invocation. No problem. He bound her again, faster than he could have even five seconds ago.

To his bigger surprise, Dumbledore and Hermione were also recovering from their death. Dumbledore was not fast enough, though. Before he had picked up his wand, Tom killed him again.

Tom turned to Harry. Hermione living again was a great opportunity for Tom to crush what remained of Harry's mind. It would make taking over his body easy. "Kill Hermione," he ordered.

Chapter 8: The end of the world

Nicolas Flamel looked at his watch. If his memory was correct, the battle should be over by now. At last the heartbreaking millennia of limited intervention were over; the children were safely gone and he did not have to be paranoid about paradoxes, at least from them. If all went well there would be just one more big time trip, creating magic. He realised he was procrastinating, and waved a very old wand over the watch; it turned into a blood red gem with an array of imperfections in the middle. "Becomus Goddus," he whispered.

The stone immediately beeped. "Invalid hairstyle error," it announced in the voice of his childhood.

"What!" exclaimed the wise old mage, losing his equanimity for the first time in centuries.

Hermione, as he still thought of her, laughed. "You must have forgotten how obnoxious you can be." There was no barb in her voice… she knew he did nothing but mean well. She waved her wand at her husband, and his hairstyle changed to that he wore when he first met her on the train to Hogwarts.

"Just kidding!" Added the stone.

The sun dimmed for seven minutes, and then the new deity looked up and smiled. Destroying death would take huge magical resources, but enough would be freed by a new interdict stopping time travel. This would have the side benefit of preventing the universe from vanishing in a paradox.

The centaurs were the first to notice the change. They looked up at points of light in the sky with horror. There was no information travelling back in time through them; they were no longer stars as far as prophecy was concerned. They were merely far off masses of fusing plasma.

Seven human seers suddenly broke off in the middle of their prophecy of an imminent end of the world. They were left with a puzzled feeling that their world had actually ended, although it certainly seemed to be still present when they looked with their prosaic eyes.

In the Hall of Prophecy, shelves full of glowing orbs darkened.

But there was light too. In Azkaban it was the brightest, and when it dimmed, there were no dementors left.

Authors note:

Technically the title should be "Harry Potter and the Cryptographic Quality Key", as there is no actual cryptography involved; just a key that has many of the properties of many cryptographic keys. But that sounds clumsy, as does "Harry Potter and the eight thousand random bits".

If you like this I have some original fiction at fictionpress, a hard Sci-Fi novel called "Artie", with mostly rational characters.